Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is בבא קמא Bava
Kama פ"א pe-aleph 81, we pick up at the very bottom line
of פ' עמוד ב', pe-amud-bet, and we're dealing with certain תקנות takkanot
that were made in order to protect the land of Israel, the
actual physical land and the landscape and also people like not raising
dogs and so on. Okay תנו רבנן, Tanna Rabbanan, last line, עשרה
תנאים התנה יהושע, asara tenayim hitna Yehoshua, Yehoshua made ten stipulations, meaning
ten
stipulations are assumed to be agreed upon when they went in to
conquer the land that these would be ruling for the entire society.
שיהיו מרעין ובחורשין, she-ye-marian u-vachorshin, so most of these as it's very
different from our משנה mishna which are restrictions to not damage others,
these are stipulations to allow people a certain degree of freedom even
relating to private property of others.
Okay, so number one is that people could go ahead and graze
their animals in the forests, we learned before that you're allowed to
own sheep and goat if you graze them in the forests, and
here you're even allowed to do it in private forests, which is
quite surprising. Okay, but presumably there was not a concern that you
weren't using it to raise crops and there was not a concern
that it would destroy the vegetation and the vegetation would grow back.
ומלקטין עצים בשדותיהם u-melaktin etzim be-sadoteihem and you could gather up sticks
in other people's property to use for firewood, now or maybe to
feed your animal if it's like I don't know hay or something,
but we'll take a look the גמרא's Gemara going to qualify a
lot of this because like maybe the owner wants to use it
for that. ומלקטין עשבים בכל מקום u-melaktin asavim be-chol makom and you
can gather up
grasses anywhere, not just in the fields, but like wherever you find
grass you can
get it to feed your animal and again we'll have to see
is that really true in all cases at the it that we
mean in again if it's a case where like it doesn't really
it's assumed it's not really going to hurt the owner it makes
sense, people have a right to do that. I mean obviously if
Yehoshua did not make this תקנה takkana they would not have the
right because it's my private property whether it goes to waste or
doesn't go to waste, but it would make sense that if nobody's
really being hurt that Yehoshua would say you don't have a right
to stop people. But the גמרא Gemara is going to qualify because
obviously there are cases where the owners could be hurt. Okay so
let's take a look.
בכל
מקום חוץ מתלתן be-chol makom chutz mi-talsan except for fenugreek when you
by removing grass that's growing near fenugreek you're going to hurt the
fenugreek. וקוטמין נטיות בכל מקום ve-kotmim nityot be-chol makom and you can
also break off like twigs
anywhere חוץ מגרופיות של זית chutz mi-grufiyot shel zayit except for branches
or sprigs of an olive tree. רש"י Rashi said you would be
breaking these off not to use
for firewood but in order to actually use for your own planting.
Again that's pretty surprising.
Okay but for the olive tree it was considered to be too
harmful. ומעין היוצא בתחילה בני אדם מסתפקין ממנו u-mayan hayotzei ba-techilla bnei
adam mistapkim mimenu now this is a really big shocker that if
a wellspring comes up by itself then that is considered to be
public property even though it is on your private
property people need water and when you find an underground well that
actually belongs to the public or at least בני אדם מסתפקין ממנו
bnei adam mistapkim mimenu means they have a right to use it
maybe you own it but they have a right to use it.
תוספות Tosafot says that if you dug a well there's other cases
in the גמרא Gemara evidence that if you were actually the one
who dug
it then then you do have a right to the water that
comes up. But really shows you about the reality about society and
at that time and how water was like a public good and
a desperate need. All right so ומחקין בימה של טבריה u-mechakin be-yama
shel tverya people could this all is this is rights like that
everybody has even though things technically would be other people's property. ומחקין
בימה של טבריה u-mechakin be-yama shel tverya like the word that you
can go hook fishing in the Tiberias even though it's on the
shores of other people ובלבד שלא יפרוס קלע ויעמיד את הספינה u-bilvad
she-lo yifros kela ve-yaamid et ha-sfina provided that you do not spread
out like types of traps which will cause the boats to get
caught in them.
ונפנין לאחורי הגדר ve-niftin leachorei ha-geder and you can go behind a
fence like a גדר geder often means like a stone fence and
relieve yourself
ונפנין ve-niftin actually means like defecate you need privacy ואפילו בשדה מלאה
כרכום ve-afilu be-sadeh mlei'ah karkom even by a field filled with saffron
saffron was so precious in the ancient world that it was literally
worth its weight in gold and nevertheless when you gotta go you
gotta go. Again I don't
know maybe
the thing provided good fertilizer but it sounds like it might have
damaged the saffron and nevertheless we allowed that to happen which is
a big shocker but this just shows it's like a כבוד הבריות
kevod habriyot type of an issue. Okay. ומהלכין בשבילי הרשות עד שתרד
רביעה שניה U'mehalchin bishvilei ha'reshut ad she'teired reviah shniyah, *Umehalchin bishvilei hareshut
ad sheterid revia shniya* and you can go in the paths of
the רשות *Reshut* which until the second rain falls. So what this
means is is that you know when the after the rain is
falling and the grain is growing you're not allowed to cut through
somebody's field you're going to damage it but after the after the
grain has been cut you know it's a field is lying fallow
then people have a right to cut through the field even because
there's not a concern that they'll damage nothing is planted and they're
not going to damage anything until you know the second rain after
the seeding at that point already then you cannot do it because
you will damage the plots the plants. Now what is רשות *Reshut*?
So רש"י *Rashi* actually says that it means permission and that it
means that people give permission to cut through the field and you
know they're path and now maybe they want you not to just
make your own path they'll make a very specific path and they're
called שבילי רשות *Shvilei reshut*. Those are the paths that people permit
you to walk through and you're allowed to you know and יהושע
Yehoshua *Yehoshua* sort of maybe they allowed you once יהושע Yehoshua *Yehoshua*
said they had to allow you but anyway it was only until
the second rain. Others say that the word רשות *Reshut* means that
they're privately owned and even though they're privately owned you're allowed to
do it. Okay ומסתלקין לצדי הדרכים מפני יסדות הדרכים *Umistalkin letzidei hadrachim
mipnei yesados hadrachim* you can go to the edges of the pathway
into private property and we're going to see that this is going
to be at a time when all of the mud you know
from the rainy season or whatever and then it becomes the summer
and it hardens and you know it's like it's a very sharp
and bumpy and hard to walk in the main path. You're allowed
to go over to the edge even though you're going into private
property.
That's יסדות *Yesados* like the pegs of the of the way. והתועה
בין הכרמים *Vehato'eh bein hakeramim* and if somebody is lost amongst the
vines in a vineyard מפסיק ועולה מפסיק ויורד *Mafsik ve'oleh mafsik veyored*
he can actually cut his way to get out of it or
cut his way to get down you know through it the vineyard
in order to get back to a street like let's say you
know you can see the street is above you but you have
no way of knowing how to get out unless but you know
you can cut yourself a straight line and then maybe you'll be
able to get back to civilization. Okay ומת מצוה קונה מקומו *Umet
mitzvah koneh mekomo* and if a person dies and you know nobody
knows whose relative it is and who the person is he has
a right to be buried wherever he dies it doesn't matter who
owns that property. Okay now we're going to unpack all of this.
שיהו מרעין בחורשין *Sheyoyu mar'in bechorshin*
that they can go ahead and graze their animals in the in
the forest that's how it connects to what we're talking about but
this is even privately owned forests. אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Pappa,
לא אמרן אלא דקה בגסה *Amar Rav Papa lo amran ela daka
begasa* that's only small animals grazing in a thick forest. אבל דקה
בדקה *Aval daka bedaka* but a small animal meaning a sheep or
a goat grazing in a thinly dense you know forest that's not
dense וגסה בגסה *Vegasa begasa* or a large animal grazing in a
dense forest לא *Lo* that's not allowed because that might damage it
too much and again if it's yours you can do it but
this is talking that it's somebody else's. וכל שכן גסה בדקה *Vechol
shekein gasa bedaka* לא *Lo* and certainly a large animal a cow
whatever grazing in a in a thin forest is not allowed for
somebody else's. ומלקטין עצים משדותיהן *Umelaktin eitzim misdotieihen* you can gather up
twigs whatever from somebody else's field. לא אמרן אלא בהיזמי והיגני *Lo
amran ela behizmei vehignei* so now we have some very logical qualifications
here that's only talking about things that are like
thornbushes. אבל בשאר עצים *Aval beshear eitzim* לא *Lo* and other wood
no you know they want it for their firewood. ואפילו בהיזמי והיגני
*Ve'afilu behizmei vehignei* and if it's thornbushes לא אמרן אלא במחוברים *Lo
amran ela bemechubarin* that's only things that are actually attached to the
ground because then okay you're going to the effort to pull them
out and you're maybe doing a favor to the owner you know
who wants thornbushes in their property. אבל בתלושין *Aval betlushin* לא *Lo*
but if they've already been pulled out then the owners maybe they
pulled it they pulled it out and they want to they want
to use it for firewood. ואפילו במחוברים *Ve'afilu bemechubarin* even if it's
attached it's growing לא אמרן אלא בלח *Lo amran ela belach* that's
only if it's moist. אבל ביבשים *Aval beyaveshim* לא *Lo* if it's
dry no because again maybe if it's dry it's much more ready
for firewood so we have to assume that the owner is going
to possibly want it so again this is not allowed for you
if you're really going to hurt the owner. ובלבד שלא ישרש *Uvelvad
shelo yesharesh*
and even if you're doing it the moist you can't go ahead
and like really uproot it in a way that damages the soil.
So the basic point is you know other than a few cases
where there was like real כבוד הבריות Kvod habriyot, *Kavod Habriot* you
know or like overriding things like the case about מת מצוה *Meis
mitzvah* or the case about you know relieving yourself most of these
is יהושע Yehoshua *Yehoshua* sort of saying like even though you privately
own it you can't stop somebody because there's a general need and
because you're not really losing anything but as soon as you're losing
something then it's not allowed at least that's what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* sort of makes clear and qualifies. Okay ומלקטין עשבים בכל מקום
חוץ משדה תלתן *Umelaktin asavim bechol makom chutz misdei tiltan* and you
can gather grasses in any place you know like like weeds and
other things that are growing up that are of no interest for
the owner except for fenugreek. Fenugreek where presumably it's helpful. So the
גמרא Gemara. says למימרא דתלתן מעלי לה עשבים Le-meimra de-tiltan ma'alei lah
asavim are you telling me that fenugreek the grasses are good? ורמינהי
U-reminhi תלתן שהעלו מיני עשבים, tiltan she-he'elu minei asavim, if fenugreek grows
up with other types of grasses, אין מחייבין אותו לעקור, ein mechayvin
oto la'akor, you do not require, I'm sorry, if fenugreek, you know,
yeah, happens to grow with other types of grasses, you do not
require somebody to uproot the fenugreek or to uproot the other grasses
because of כלאים. kilayim. Why? Because it's happened by itself, you didn't
plant it. So therefore the only problem with כלאים kilayim is if
you want them to be growing. But if it's actually damaging and
you don't want them to be growing together, then it's not a
כלאים kilayim problem since you didn't plant it. So you see that
it's actually damaging. אמר רב ירמיה לא קשיא, Amar Rav Yirmiyah lo
kashya, it's not difficult. כאן לזרע כאן לזירן, Kan le-zera kan le-zirin,
it depends whether it's for the seed or whether it's for the
stalk. For the seed it damages, for the stalk it's good. לזרע
קשו ליה עשבים, Le-zera kashu leh asavim, for the if you want
it for the seed it damages, so that's the case where it's
not a כלאים kilayim problem. לזירן, Le-zirin, but if you want it,
if you want the fenugreek for the stalk, I lost my place,
לזירן קשו ליה עשבים, le-zirin kashu leh asavim,
so for the seed the grass is
bad דמחחש לה de-machchesh lah because it weakens the seeds, so it's
counterproductive. So that's the case where it's not a כלאים kilayim problem
and you would be allowed to uproot the uproot the grasses. I'm
sorry, so let me write that, לזרע קשו ליה עשבים דמחחש לה.
le-zera kashu leh asavim de-machchesh lah. For the seed the grass is
bad that it weakens it, so if somebody is growing it for
the seed it's not a, well, if it happened by itself it's
not a כלאים kilayim problem if the person's interested in the fenugreek
for the seed because it's damaging, the grass, and you would be
allowed to pull out the grass. לזירן, Le-zirin, if somebody's interested for
the stalk, מעלו ליה, ma'alu leh, the grass is good and in
that case you're not allowed to pull out the grass and it
would be a כלאים kilayim problem, okay, if it was really of
a different מין. min. דכי קיימי ביני עשבים De-chi kaymi beinei asavim
because when the fenugreek is growing between, you know, grass, מירכבא, mirkava,
then it will sort of spread out on the other vegetation and
it actually helps the stalk. So in a case where it's not
a כלאים kilayim problem whatever, that's a case where the grass is
good and you cannot remove the grass. So אי בעית אימא כאן
לאדם כאן לבהמה, I ba'it eima kan le-adam kan le-behemah, or a
difference between whether it's growing for human consumption or for animal consumption.
כיון דלבהמה הוא, Keivan de-le-behemah hu,
why would that make the difference? Because if you're growing it for
animal consumption, דזרע עשבים נמי מיבעי ליה, de-zara asavim nami miba'ei leh,
so the one, דזרע, de-zara, the one who planted it also wants
the grass to feed the animal. All right, so therefore you know
don't do, if it is for animal, that's when Yehoshua said that
the תקנה takanah did not allow you to pull out the grass.
So the גמרא Gemara says ומנא ידיענא, U-mena yediana, where how do
you know which is which? So אמר רב פפא שורי דשורי לאדם,
Amar Rav Papa shurei de-shurei le-adam, if it's in rows then it
is for human consumption. לאו שורי דשורי, lav shurei de-shurei, if it's
not in rows, לבהמה, le-behemah, it's for animals. I don't know why
that would be different. I also don't know how the how you
would know whether you want it for seed or for stalks, the
earlier answer the גמרא. Okay, וכותם נטיעה בכל מקום חוץ מגרופיות של
זית, Ve-kotem neti'ah be-chol makom chutz mi-grufiyot shel zayit, and you
can, you know, cut off a twig in any place from a
growing tree except from, except a shoot of an olive tree. Okay,
so the גמרא says like this, פירש רב תנחום ורב ביריי משום
זקן אחד בזית כביצה. Perash Rav Tanchum ve-Rav Birai mishum zaken echad
be-zayit ke-beitzah.
When it's talking about an olive, it has to be a כביצה.
ke-beitzah. Exactly what this means is a whole debate. Anyway, one way
to understand this is you can only cut off, you know, the
size of a twig the size of an egg. Now the problem
is we just said before you can't cut it off from an
olive tree, so it's a whole complicated exactly, you know, what this
is talking about. Does it mean that the thickness of the twig
has to be a כביצה ke-beitzah and then it's allowed?
Not clear. ובקנים ובגפנים מן הפקק ולמעלה, U-vi-kanim u-vi-gefenim min ha-paka u-le-ma'alah,
if it's other types of reeds or or grapevines, מן הפקק ולמעלה,
min ha-paka u-le-ma'alah, you can cut it off from like where it's
got the little פקק, paka, like the little knuckle, the little bump
and above. ושאר כל האילנות מן עוביו של אילן ולא מחודו, Ve-sha'ar
kol ha-ilanot min ovyo shel ilan ve-lo me-chudo,
you can do it from like the inside of the tree says
רש״י Rashi or different explanations, but not from the top of the
tree. All right, so cutting it off in a way, it's again
there's whole debates about what every single one of these means, but
the bottom line is you can cut off a little twig if
it's not going to injure the tree and not consider like something
that the owner would want for himself. Okay, ולא מחודו של אילן
מן חדש שאינו עושה פירות ולא מן ישן שהוא עושה פירות. Ve-lo
me-chudo shel ilan min chadash she-eino oseh peirot ve-lo min yashan she-hu
oseh peirot. You can only cut it off from a new twig
which is not already growing fruit, not from a twig, not from
a branch that fruit is growing from. ממקום שאינו רואה את החמה,
Mi-makom she-eino roeh et ha-chamah, and you have to grow it off
from place not exposed to the sun, because the stuff exposed to
the sun obviously will produce better fruit and the owner would not
want you to break it off. ולא ממקום שהוא רואה את החמה,
Ve-lo mi-makom she-hu roeh et ha-chamah,
you have to break it off from a place that doesn't see
the sun and
not from the place that's exposed to the sun, שנאמר וממגד תבואות
שמש, she-ne'emar u-mi-meged tevu'ot shamesh, you know, from the sweetness of the
of the growth of the sun. So therefore it has to be
from the inside. side of the tree and from a part that,
you know, again it would be not injuring the owner to be
breaking off a little twig. ומאינה יוצא Uma'inah yotzei top of פ"א
עמוד ב'. Pei Aleph Amud Bet. ומאינה יוצא תחילת בני העיר מסתפקין
ממנו Uma'inah yotzei techilat benei ha'ir mistapkin mimenu and if a new
well, the owners, you know, the people can have a right to
use it, even if it's on private property. אמר רבה בר רב
הונא ונותן לו דמים Amar Rabba bar Rav Huna venoten lo damim
and but you have to pay for it. It's still his, I
mean they have a right because people have a right, you know,
water is a necessity, but he still owns it. ולית הלכתא כוותיה
Velait hilchata kevateih we don't rule that way. You know that was
maybe that sort of resonates for us that we are deep believers
in private property, but it actually says no, you know they have
a right. But again it's not clear that it's publicly owned. How
much water can they take from it? Can they take enough to
do their laundry? Can they take enough to shower every day? You
know that's not clear. It sounds like he still owns it, but
they have a right for a certain degree of usage of the
water. Okay. ומחכין בימה של טבריה Umechakin beyama shel Tverya you can
go like fishing with a hook. That's, you know, normal like cast
fishing in the ocean of Tverya. ובלבד שלא יפרוס קלע ויעמיד את
הספינה Uvilvad shelo yifros kela veya'amid et hasfina provided that you do
not go ahead, you know, and put out types of traps that
will cause the boats to get caught, אבל צד הוא ברשתות ובמכמורות
Aval tzad hu berishatot uvimichmorot
but you can use like nets. So there's a, you know, there's
a type of like a box trap which can catch a boat,
but nets would be allowed. Now the way Tosafos explains this he
says there are three levels. Like fishing with a cast fishing anybody
can do, even if it's not your private property. You can go
into somebody else's private property and, you know, fish off of their
shore, you know, in the Kinneret.
The big type of wooden or, you know, box traps or whatever
they would be, nobody is allowed to do even if you have
the property that is around the Kinneret because that would cause the
ships to get caught up. But if you are the owner you
are allowed to at least do net fishing. Okay. So non-owners can
do cast fishing, owners can do net fishing, nobody can do the
type of like big traps. תנו רבנן בראשונה התנו שבטים זה עם
זה Tanu Rabanan berishona hitnu shevatim zeh im zeh originally the tribes
made a condition with one another. שלא יפרוס קלע ויעמיד את הספינה
Shelo yifros kela veya'amid et hasfina not to spread out this type
of a, you know, of a big trap that would cause the
boats to get caught, אבל צד הוא ברשתות ובמכמורות Aval tzad hu
berishatot uvimichmorot but people did have a right to use nets and
other types of traps. תנו רבנן ימה של טבריה בחלקו של נפתלי
היתה Tanu Rabanan yama shel Tverya bechelko shel Naftali hayta
the Kinneret fell in Naftali's portion in Eretz Yisrael. ולא עוד אלא
שנטל מלא חבל חרם בדרומה Velo od ela shenatal melo chevel cherem
bidroma and not only that, but he even got a piece of
the, you know, of the shore at on the south, even though
his portion was really, you know, the east of Eretz Yisrael, but
he also got cut into the south of Tverya, of the south
of the shore. לקיים מה שנאמר ים ודרום ירשה Lekayem mah shene'emar
yam vedarom yerasha
he will inherit both the west, meaning the west of the Kinneret,
the shore of the Kinneret on the west, and the south of
the Kinneret. תני רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר תלושין שבהרים בחזקת כל
השבטים הן עומדים ומחוברין בחזקת אותו השבט Tani Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
omer telushin shebeharim bechezkat kol hashevatim hen omdim umichubarin bechezkat oto hashevet
things that were detached in the mountains all of the tribes had
rights to it, things that were attached belonged to that tribe. Rashi
says it means for the like when they went into Eretz Yisrael
initially and conquered Eretz Yisrael, so anything that was like that wasn't
part of the landscape was considered the booty of the land, you
know, and the property that they seized from the entire land, and
that interestingly was not based did not get divided based on whose
portion and whose tribe it fell in, that got divided equally. At
least that's the way Rashi explains it, a much broader understanding than
just specifically like a, you know, like branches that had fallen off.
Okay. You could have ואין לך כל שבט ושבט מישראל שאין לו
בהר ובשפלה ובנגב ובעמק ve'ein lecha kol shevet veshevet miYisrael she'ein lo
behar uvashfela uvanegev uvayemek
and no tribe in Israel did not get a, you know, different,
you know,
the range of the different landscapes available in Israel. There's no tribe
that did not get all of the following: both, you know, mountains
and lowlands and drylands and valleys. שנאמר פנו וסעו לכם ובאו הר
האמורי ואל כל שכניו Shene'emar pnu use'u lachem uvau har ha'Emori ve'el
kol shechenav go into the mountain of the Emori and all of
its neighbors. בערבה בהר ובשפלה ובנגב ובחוף הים ba'arava bahar uvashfela uvanegev
uvachof hayam and it mentions all of those. Of course not everybody
got the חוף הים. chof hayam. Okay, but everybody is going in
and getting that, so everybody is going to get a range of
the different landscapes. וכן אתה מוצא בכנענים ובפרזים ובאמוריים שלפניהם Vechen ata
motzei baKena'anim uvaprizim uvEmoriyim shelifnehem and that was true also about, you
know, the tribes that inherited it before the seven Canaanite nations. שנאמר
ואל כל שכניו Shene'emar ve'el kol shechenav all of its neighbors. אמר
שכניו הכי הוו Amar shechenav hachi havu its neighbors also had all
of... all of those different landscapes. I don't know exactly what it
does with חוף הים, Chof hayam, and it doesn't seem like it
actually was accurate and true to how the land was divided, but
okay. ונפני לאחורי הגדר V'nifni l'achorei hageder and you can relieve yourself
on the back, you know, on the other side of the stone
fence. ואפילו בשדה שמלאה כרכום, Va'afillu bisdeh shemlei'ah karkom, even in a
field filled with saffron. אמר רב אחא בר יעקב, Amar Rav Acha
bar Yaakov, לא נצרכא אלא ליטול הימנו צרור. Lo nitzrecha ela litol
heimenu tzror. This is not needed, meaning it's so obvious that this
is permissible, not so obvious to me. Is it so obvious because
of כבוד הבריות, Kvod habriyot or is it so obvious because maybe,
you know, it ultimately helps the field and it fertilizes it? So
he says the real חידוש Chiddush here is that you can take
a stone from the stone wall and use it to wipe yourself.
That that's allowed. Okay. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, ואפילו בשבת,
Va'afillu b'Shabbos,
even on Shabbos. It's a classic example of כבוד הבריות overriding a
דרבנן DeRabbanan because obviously the stone is מוקצה. Muktzah. מר זוטרא חסידא
שקיל ומהדר. Mar Zutra Chasida shakil u'mehader. מר זוטרא Mar Zutra was
a חסיד, Chassid, so he, you know, took it and he wiped
himself with it and then he put it back in the wall,
I guess in a way that, you know, it was not exposed,
you know, what he had wiped himself on. ואמר ליה לשמעיה, V'amar
lei l'shamayei, and then he said to his attendant, זיל שריקיה, Zil
shrikei, go ahead and plaster over it. Okay, obviously not on Shabbos.
So plaster over it so that, because now he just used it
to wipe himself, so he wanted it to go back in the
wall, but he obviously did not want it to be disgusting for
other people, so he plastered over it. Okay. ומהלכין בשבילי הרשות עד
שתרד רביעה שניה,
and you go into the paths of that which are either paths
that you have permission to go into, you know, that or are
owned by private people. Anyway, you can cut through the fields before
the planting season until the second rain has come down. אמר רב
פפא, והדידן אפילו טליא דקשלא. V'hadidan afillu talya d'kashla. But our fields,
actually, even after there's just been dew, it would be difficult to
walk on. It doesn't need to wait for the second rain, so
obviously you can't walk on it at any time when there it
could do damage to the field. It's only in times when nobody
is hurt by you cutting through their yard. Okay. ומסלקים לצידי הדרכים
מפני יתדות הדרכים, U'mesalkim l'tzidei hadrachim mipnei yetidot hadrachim,
and you go to the edge of the way because of the
pegs, meaning, you know, the sharp mud that has hardened, so you
can walk on private property to avoid that. שמואל ורב יהודה הוו
שקלי ואזלי באורחא. Shmuel v'Rav Yehuda havah shakli v'azlei b'orcha. שמואל Shmuel
and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda were, you know, going and walking on
the way. הוה מסתלק שמואל לצידי הדרכים, Havah mistallek Shmuel l'tzidei hadrachim,
and he walked over to the edge of the path because it
was the dry season and it was very bumpy and sharp, like
we've taught. Now, by the way, remember that this was תנאי יהושע,
Tna'ei Yehoshua, יהושע Yehoshua made this stipulation in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Here we're outside of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Before we said that
בבל, Bavel, they treated themselves like ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for the
restrictions that were in the משנה Mishnah about the small animals. Here
we're talking about special permissions, but apparently שמואל Shmuel is assuming that
whatever permissions were true about יהושע Yehoshua we can somehow assume that
it was implicit in any Jewish society, or certainly in בבל, Bavel,
but that's itself fascinating. Okay. So he went and he went to
the sides. אמר ליה רב יהודה לשמואל, Amar lei Rav Yehuda l'Shmuel,
so that's what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda is going to challenge him
with. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, תנאים שהתנה יהושע אפילו בבבל?
Tna'im shehitna Yehoshua afillu b'Bavel? Do you think the conditions יהושע Yehoshua
made, were they in בבל? Bavel? I mean, obviously they weren't, יהושע
was only ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. אמר ליה, Amar lei, שאני אומר
אפילו בחוץ לארץ. Sha'ani omer afillu b'chootz la'aretz. Yes, I mean, I
say even in חוץ לארץ. Chootz la'aretz. Now again, is he claiming
יהושע said this, you know, or is he saying that we should
assume that any Jewish community, you know, is implicitly going to be
operating with these parameters? רבי ורבי חייא הוו שקלי ואזלי באורחא. Rebbi
v'Rebbi Chiya havah shakli v'azlei b'orcha. רבי Rebbi and רבי חייא Rebbi
Chiya were going on the way. אסתלק לצידי הדרכים, Istalek l'tzidei hadrachim,
and they went to the side. This is in ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. This is רבי יהודה הנשיא. Rebbi Yehuda HaNasi. הוה קא מפסע
ואזל רבי יהודה בן קנוסא. Havah ka mafsa v'azil Rebbi Yehuda ben
Kenusa.
Now רבי יהודה בן קנוסא, Rebbi Yehuda ben Kenusa, he was not
going to the side. He was going in the middle of the
road, and he was like, you know, like what you do in
a river, like you jump from one rock to the next. He
was jumping from like one place to the next and navigating all
of these bumpy road.
So he was coming in front of them. אמר ליה רבי לרבי
חייא, Amar lei Rebbi l'Rebbi Chiya, so רבי Rebbi said to רבי
חייא, Rebbi Chiya, מיהו זה שמפגין גדולה בפנינו? Mihu zeh she'mapgin gedulah
b'faneinu? Who is this that's showing himself off to be such a
big shot? Oh, he's so פרום frum he can't go on the
side of the road, and he's doing it in our presence, like
suggesting, like if he wants to do it on his own, fine.
But here, we רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rebbi Yehuda HaNasi, you know, the
greatest the political and, you know, leader and the rabbinic leader of
the generation and רבי חייא, Rebbi Chiya, they're on the side of
the road and he's too פרום frum to do it? So that's
like a little bit of an affront.
אמר ליה רבי חייא, Amar lei Rebbi Chiya, שמא רבי יהודה בן
קנוסא תלמידי הוא. Shema Rebbi Yehuda ben Kenusa talmidi hu. Maybe it's
רבי יהודה בן קנוסא Rebbi Yehuda ben Kenusa my student. וכל מעשיו
לשם שמים. V'chol ma'asav l'sheim shamayim. And because he's, you know, believe
me, he's doing it לשם שמים, L'sheim shamayim, he's not trying to
show that he's better than us, he really, really just likes, you
know, is super careful about these things. כי מטו לגביה חזיו. Ki
matu legabeih chazyuh. When they came to him they saw, yes,
תקי Takei it
was. בגזירא דפרזלא begezeira deparzla would cut off your legs with an
iron like a hatchet with an iron axe.
So you're jumping with your legs and you're trying to show you're
better than us. So if you were anybody else I would have
said it was an affront, but with you obviously didn't mean it
literally. רש״י Rashi says he means he would have put you in
נידוי, niduy, but anyway but you're doing it I trust you know
I trust Rav Yehuda that you're doing it לשם שמים. leshem shamayim.
Okay. התועה בין הכרמים מפסג ועולה מפסג ויורד, Hatoueh bein hakramim mefaseg
veoleh mefaseg veyored, somebody who's erring in the vineyard you know you
can go ahead and cut your way out. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan:
הרואה חברו תועה בין הכרמים מפסג ועולה מפסג ויורד, Haroeh chaveiro toueh
bein hakramim mefaseg veoleh mefaseg veyored, means if you saw somebody sort
of get who's lost in the vineyards מפסג ועולה מפסג ויורד mefaseg
veoleh mefaseg veyored you can cut your way in and get him
and then cut your way out עד שמעלהו לעיר או לדרך ad
shemaalehu le'ir o laderech until you get him back to a town
or to the road. וכן הוא Vechen hu and same the person
himself שתעה בין הכרמים shetaah bein hakramim that's lost מפסג ועולה מפסג
ויורד עד שיעלהו לעיר או לדרך. mefaseg veoleh mefaseg veyored ad sheyaalehu
le'ir o laderech.
Okay you can do it yourself for yourself. מאי וכן? Mai vechen?
What do you mean also you? I mean if somebody else can
save you you can save yourself. No, מהו דתימא, mahu deteima, I
might have thought חברו הוא דידע להיכא מסלק, chaveiro hu deyada leheicha
mesalek, דלא ליפסג, delo lifsag,
if your friend is coming from outside the vineyard he knows how
to cut a path to get to you and how to get
back out. So him we'll allow it won't be destructive or won't
be overly destructive. אבל הוא דלא ידע להיכא קסליק, Aval hu delo
yada leheicha kasalik, you don't know where the heck you're going so
לא ליפסג, lo lifsag, so you don't have a right to cut
your way out, you're going to do a lot of destruction, you're
totally lost. נהדרי נהדרא בי מצרי, Nehadrei nehadra bemetzrei, you should have
to go by you know get yourself into the edges of the
vineyard and even if it you know it's going to get you
you know even though it seems to you that that's going to
cause you much much much more distance you know and you think
you have a short path out if you would cut your way,
since you don't know what you're doing maybe you'd be forced to
do that. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan we don't say that,
that even if you don't know what you're doing you know you
can go the way you think is right even if it means
you have to cut your way through. Okay so the Gemara says
now: הא דאורייתא היא. Ha deoraisa hi. What do you mean that
this is a תנאי של יהושע? tenai shel Yehoshua? Saving somebody is
a דאורייתא. deoraisa. דתניא Detanya we learned in a ברייתא, braisa, השבת
גופו מנין? hashavas gufo minayin? How do you know you have an
obligation to return somebody's the same way you have an obligation to
return their lost object you have an obligation to return you know
their body to them? So or this is a little type different
type of a השבה, hashava, you're returning him to his town. It's
not clear whether the Gemara thinks it's like פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh
but whatever but helping somebody saving somebody who's lost, how do you
know you're obligated? תלמוד לומר והשבותו, Talmud lomar vahashevoso, you return him,
you return him to himself. So so the Gemara says: Yes you
do have an obligation to help him דאורייתא. deoraisa. דאורייתא הוא דקאי
בי מצרי. Deoraisa hu dekai bemetzrei. דאורייתא Deoraisa but for דאורייתא deoraisa
you would have to do it without damaging somebody else's property, you'd
have to do it by going at the edges. אתא הוא, Asa
hu, came יהושע תיקן דמפסג ועולה מפסג ויורד, tikein demefaseg veoleh mefaseg
veyored, he established that you can actually cut your way through to
get in and out and that was his תקנה. takana. Okay we
will stop here for now.